Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is ל, Lamed, 30.
We pick up on כט עמוד ב. Chaf-Tet Amud Bet. We're a
little behind. We pick up where איתמר, itmar, it is about 15
lines down from the top. It starts with the words דאינון שנים
תקנה ולכנת. de-inun shanim tikneh ve-laknat. Now there's an asterisk, איתמר. itmar.
It's sort of almost exactly opposite the big גמרא Gemara symbol in
רש״י. Rashi. Okay, and basically the משנה Mishnah is talking about the
הלכות halachos of buying back your field, which is in the end
of בהר Behar during the period of the יובל, Yovel, and you
have to do it and you have a right to do it
after two
years, force the person to sell you back your שדה אחוזה, sadeh
achuza, but you are prohibited from doing it for the first two
years, not just you're not able but prohibited. Okay, now we're going
to have a debate which is something we've quoted earlier. Let's take
a look. איתמר המוכר שדהו בשנת היובל עצמה. itmar ha-mocher sadehu bi-shnat
ha-yovel atzmah. Let's say he tried selling his field during the יובל
Yovel itself. Right, when the יובל Yovel comes, it reverts the field.
Let's say you tried to sell it on the יובל Yovel year.
רב אמר מכורה ויוצא. Rav amar mechura ve-yotza. רב Rav says the
sale goes through and then immediately afterwards the יובל Yovel kicks in
and gives you back your field, which basically means that the guy,
you know, paid his money and he's out his money, and it's
sort of like a buyer beware. Yes, you could buy the field,
it's able to be binding and a second later it goes back.
So the sale was valid, you keep the money that the guy
paid you, and then you get your field back. All right,
that's what רב Rav says. ושמואל אמר אינה מכורה כל עיקר. u-Shmuel
amar einah mechura kol ikar. No, the sale didn't even take effect.
A sale cannot, of a שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuza, cannot be effective
during a year where the whole point is that the שדה אחוזה
sadeh achuza reverts to the owners. Okay, מאי טעמא דשמואל? mai ta'ama
de-Shmuel? What's the reasoning of שמואל? Shmuel? קל וחומר. kal vachomer. It's
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
ומה מכורה כבר יוצאה, u-mah mechura kvar yotza'ah, something that has already
been sold goes back, שאינה מכורה אינו דין שלא תימכר, she-einah mechura
eino din she-lo timacher, how much more so should something that has
not been sold not, the sale not be effective. It's not an
exact קל וחומר kal vachomer because an exact קל וחומר kal vachomer
is you apply the same law. So the קל וחומר kal vachomer
would be something that was already sold goes back, certainly something that
you're selling now goes back. But it's a, you certainly understand the
intuitive logic of it. The whole point of the יובל Yovel is
to make, give you back your field, so how much more so
should this sale not even be effective on the יובל. Yovel.
Oh, thank you, lifesaver here.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, ולרב לא אמרינן קל וחומר
כי האי גוונא? u-le-Rav lo amrinan kal vachomer ki hai gavna? Would
רב Rav say you don't say such a קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
And again, the point being such a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, a
קל וחומר kal vachomer that would say that it would prevent it
from even being effective. והתניא, ve-hatanya, I'll give you a proof where
everybody agrees you say that type of logic. יכול
ימכור אדם את בתו כשהיא נערה? yachol yimkor adam et bito keshe-hi
na'arah? Okay, let's go, we can't get away from selling the daughter.
So maybe the הלכה halacha is is that a man can sell
his daughter as a Hebrew slave when she's under age, before she's
a נערה. na'arah. Once she's a נערה, na'arah, 12 years and a
day and she has pubic hairs or whatever, then she goes free.
So she goes free if she were sold and she becomes a
נערה, na'arah, she goes free. Now what's the הלכה? halacha? Can he
sell her, let's say he hasn't sold her yet, can he sell
her if she's already a נערה? na'arah? So say no, קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. אמרת קל וחומר. amarta kal vachomer. ומה מכורה
כבר יוצאה, u-mah mechura kvar yotza'ah, if
when she was already sold that's enough for making her go free
because the idea, presumably the implicit logic is that one cannot own
her as a נערה, na'arah, אשתא דאינה מכורה אינו דין שלא תימכר,
ashta de-einah mechura eino din she-lo timacher,
now in the case where she hasn't even been sold,
how much more so should he not be able to sell her.
So you see, he says that logic by selling an underage daughter,
so he should say this logic by selling a field in the
יובל Yovel that it shouldn't go through. So someone says no, התם
לא הדרא מיזבנא, hatam lo hadra mi-zavna, הכא הדרא מיזבנא. hacha hadra
mi-zavna. There,
once she hits that age, the whole point is that she totally
leaves the father's control and she becomes a person in her own
right, and therefore there's a logic to say that since she's hitting
that age, she should be now completely free from the father. But
the case of the field, even if he can't sell it during
the יובל, Yovel, he'll be able to sell it after the יובל,
Yovel, so he basically always remains in control of that field, and
therefore the idea that on the יובל Yovel it's completely out of
his control is not the same type of compelling logic as the
idea of the girl that hits the age of נערה, na'arah, because
there it's just for that period, so therefore maybe he will be
able to sell it and it will revert to him. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, מיתיבי. meitivei.
Okay, so that's the debate. So we haven't proven it one way
or another. Let's try to prove it. אחר היובל שנים תקנה. achar
ha-yovel shanim tikneh.
So it says, so this is quoting like a hybrid of the
פסוקים, pesukim, here I'll quote you the פסוק pasuk exactly. Oh, this
is
again,
this is missing the key pages. I'm sorry.
Somebody didn't like that part. Okay,
so.
What do they use the daughter and not a slave?
A slave doesn't go free after and a slave sells himself.
Yeah, yeah, but it's not but but there's no logic. It's not
like a particular period where he can't sell himself. It's the seventh
year from the time of
sale, right?
Any of us at any time could sell ourselves as a slave.
Right, it's not the logic like once this period hits, sales don't
go through or sales revert. I mean it's all subjected to the
time seven years from the time of sale. So if you were
to do a new sale now, you'd start the clock again.
So if a father sold his daughter at the age of 11
years and 364 days, she will be a slave for one day.
Right. Well, it's all, you know, you have to know the rules
and buyer beware. Okay. But anyway, the תורה Torah says like this,
it says, wait a minute. So could it would it have been
the way
of a slave? Why is the daughter different?
Because she's going to hit her age.
But
not for a slave. Hold on, I'm sorry, she can't be resold
again.
Once she reaches that, she can no longer be in that category.
In fact, she can't even be sold a second time. Yeah.
Well, she
can.
Oh, here it is.
Okay, I'm sorry, I was going too far. Here's the פסוק. pasuk.
וכי תמכרו ממכר לעמיתך או קנה מיד עמיתך אל תונו איש את
אחיו. V'chi timkeru mimkar l'amitecha o kano miyad amitecha al tonu ish
et achiv. If you sell something to or buy something from your
friend, do not overcharge. Now, the גמרא Gemara learns this that this
is talking about chattel, but the simple context of the פסוקים pesukim
is talking about land. And here's why you might overcharge, because you'll
forget the context of the יובל. Yovel. So don't overcharge because there's
only the number of years till the יובל. Yovel. במספר שנים אחר
היובל תקנה מאת עמיתך. B'mispar shanim achar haYovel tikneh me'et amitecha. According
to the years that are following the that you're after the יובל,
Yovel, you should purchase. במספר שני תבואת ימכר לך. B'mispar shnei tvuot
yimkor lach. He's selling you the number of years till the יובל.
Yovel. That's where we get the idea במספר שני תבואות. B'mispar shnei
tvuot. שני, Shnei, not two, but years in the plural, that you
have two years of absolute use before it can be forced back.
לפי רוב השנים תרבה מקנתו. L'fi rov hashanim tarbeh miknato. According to
the large number of years you should pay more money. ולפי מעט
השנים תמעיט מקנתו. U'l'fi m'at hashanim tam'it miknato. If there's a small
number of years, pay less. כי מספר תבואות הוא מוכר לך. Ki
mispar tvuot hu mocher lach. He's basically just selling you a certain
number of years because in the end you'll get it back in
the יובל. Yovel. Okay, so those are the פסוקים pesukim and then
the next פסוקים pesukim talk about being גואל, go'el, forcing the guy
to sell it back once you've sold it. So let's take a
look now at the גמרא. Gemara. מיתיבי. Meitivei. אחר היובל שנים תקנה.
Achar haYovel shanim tikneh.
So that's selecting particular words out of the פסוק. pasuk. After the
יובל Yovel you should buy it for years. רש״י Rashi says that
אחר היובל, achar haYovel, you know, the actual full פסוק pasuk is,
what's the full פסוק? pasuk? It's במספר שנים אחר היובל תקנה מאת
עמיתך. B'mispar shanim achar haYovel tikneh me'et amitecha.
Okay,
so after the יובל Yovel you shall buy it for years. מלמד
שמוכרין סמוך ליובל. Melamed shemochrin samuch l'Yovel.
So if you just had that פסוק, pasuk, you would say fine,
you can sell right after the יובל Yovel for the full 50
years. מופלג מן היובל מנין. Muflag min haYovel minayin. How do I
know you can sell even if you're in somewhere in the middle
of a cycle? תלמוד לומר לפי רוב השנים ולפי מעט השנים. Talmud
lomar l'fi rov hashanim u'l'fi m'at hashanim. Okay, it goes whether there's
a lot of years or few years, you can sell anytime during
the cycle. Now the ברייתא braita goes on. ובשנת היובל עצמה לא
ימכור. U'bishnat haYovel atzmah lo yimkor. But don't sell during the יובל
Yovel itself. ואם מכר אינה מכורה. V'im machar einah mechurah. And if
you tried to sell during the יובל Yovel itself, it doesn't go
through. So here you have a ברייתא braita that explicitly says that
it doesn't go through, like שמואל. Shmuel. So אמר לך רב, amar
lach Rav, רב Rav would say to you, אינה מכורה למספר שני
תבואות אבל מכורה היא ויוצאה. Einah mechurah l'mispar shnei tvuot aval mechurah
hi v'yotza.
It's not sold for the law of being able to be retained
for two years, right? If you normally sell something, what's the law?
The law is is that the buyer gets two years of unimpeded
use before you can buy it back. So רב Rav is saying,
ah, if you sell it during the יובל, Yovel, you might say
like this, fine, I get it back, but the buyer could at
least say look, every sale allows me a minimum of two years.
So after the יובל Yovel is over, give me at least my
two years of use. Okay, so which also raises an interesting question.
Let's say you sell it within one year of the יובל. Yovel.
How does this rule of two years work? Because we normally think
the two years rule is a limit, here's the conceptual shift. We
normally think the two years rule is a limit to when I
can exercise my right to force you to sell it back. It's
not an entitlement that you have to get all two years out
of it. Okay, it limits my right. But here the גמרא Gemara
says no, maybe it's an entitlement, whenever you have a purchase you're
entitled always to two years. So if that's true, maybe if I
sell it during the יובל, Yovel, so when it says here that
it doesn't work during the יובל, Yovel, it doesn't mean it doesn't
work. It works and it reverts. It doesn't work to give you
your two years after the יובל. Yovel. Okay, so that's in the
way what it means it doesn't work. אינה מכורה למספר שני תבואות
אבל מכורה היא ויוצאה. Einah mechurah l'mispar shnei tvuot aval mechurah hi
v'yotza. It does go through and then it reverts and I get
to keep the money. ואי דבונא מזדבנא. V'ei d'buna mizdabna. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute,
if it really was sold, תקום ברשותיה דבתר יובל ובתר יובל ניכול
שני תבואות ונהדרה. Takum birshutei d'vatar Yovel u'vatar Yovel neichol shnei tvuot
v'nahadrah. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute And if it really
was sold, then why isn't he entitled to his two years? What
do you mean to say, oh, it means that he doesn't get
his two years? He should hold on to it until after the
יובל, Yovel, use it for two years, and then give it back.
בלא תניא, B'lo tanya, do we not teach in a ברייתא, Baraita,
אכל שנה אחת לפני היובל, achal shana achat lifnei ha'Yovel, what if
he buys it one year before the יובל Yovel and he had
one year of produce, משלימין לו שנה אחרת אחר היובל, mashlimin lo
shana acheret achar Yovel,
you give him one more year after the יובל. Yovel. So why
not in this case, if you say the sale worked, why not
give him two years after the יובל? Yovel? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, התם נחית לאכילה, hatam nachit l'achila,
there at least he started to make use of it. So once
he starts to make use of it, he's entitled for two years.
הכא לא נחית לאכילה, hacha lo nachit l'achila, here he never did,
the very second the sale took effect, it reverted. So therefore he
doesn't get that entitlement. So this is quite fascinating, even without the
רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel.
We never would have expected this. It sounded like the principle was,
as I said, that the two years was limiting my right to
exercise, you know, my right to force you to sell it back.
Now we're saying, but not that somehow you always get two years.
Now we're saying that no, if you bought it right before the
יובל, Yovel, you started using it, you are entitled to finish up
those two years after the יובל. Yovel. So even though the field
goes back automatically. Right. No, and conceptually, right, I
mean, how do we even explain it conceptually? I don't think we
would say that my, it's postponed in reverting to me until you've
used the two years. I mean, I guess you could say that,
but to me that would be, you know, very difficult to say
that the יובל Yovel doesn't give me back my field. That's the
whole idea of the יובל. Yovel. I would more say that I
get it back during the יובל, Yovel, but you still, you know,
any purchase that took place entitles you to a minimum of two
years, which is quite interesting, even if it's a purchase a week
or a month before the יובל. Yovel. I'd rather conceptually say I
get it back, but you're entitled for a two-year use. Anyway, that's
a fascinating idea, which we would not have expected. And now it's
just saying that according to רב, Rav, that would not apply if
he sold it on the יובל Yovel itself, because then that whole,
you never even began to have that right in the field. All
right, now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר רב, Amar Rav, so
now we have this debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל
Shmuel says it doesn't take effect and the guy keeps his money.
רב Rav says it takes effect, I get the money, I the
seller, and then the field immediately goes back to me. אמר רב
ענן, Amar Rav Anan, שמע מינה דמר שמואל, shema mina d'mar Shmuel,
we've heard two teachings of the master שמואל, Shmuel, two similar teachings,
תרתי, tartei, two teachings. חדא הא, chada ha, one which we just
taught, that the sale doesn't take effect. ואידך, ve'idach, and the other
one, המוכר עבדו לעובדי כוכבים או לחוץ לארץ יצא לחירות. hamocher avdo
l'ovdei kochavim o l'chutz la'aretz yatza l'cherut.
That if somebody sells his slave to a non-Jew or outside of
Israel, then the slave goes free. Why? Because a slave here, a
כנעני Kena'ani slave, is obligated in מצוות, mitzvot, mostly in most מצוות.
mitzvot. And therefore, if you force, if you sell them to a
non-Jew where they won't be able to fulfill their מצוות, mitzvot, or
even to חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz where they won't have the opportunity
to do as many מצוות, mitzvot, then they made a fine on
the owner and forced you to, because of this injustice, to free
your slave. Okay, so now the question is, חדא, chada,
in one case, הדרי זביני, hadri zvinei, the sale reverts itself. וחדא
לא הדרי זביני, ve'chada lo hadri zvinei, meaning in one case the
sale never took effect, and the other case it did take effect,
but you still have to address the situation. Now, the most logical
thing of course to say is, because we've until now been saying
that in the case of שמיטה, Shmita, of יובל, Yovel, the sale
didn't take effect, keep your money, sale didn't take effect. In the
case of the slave, it would sound like the sale took effect,
but now you the owner have a responsibility somehow to buy the
slave back and to free the slave or something of that effect.
Okay, but the question is, it's not so clear which one did
it take effect and which one did it not take effect. Either
one you have to deal with the consequences. Okay, ולא ידענא הי
מינייהו, v'lo yadana hai mineihu,
which one is which? Which one did the sale revert, never take
effect, and which one did it take effect and then you have
to go ahead and deal with it? So אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, נשמעינן, nishmi'inan, let's us try to figure it out. מדיתניא
בברייתא, mi d'tanya b'braita, we taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, המוכר עבדו
לחוץ לארץ או לחוץ לארץ יצא לחירות. hamocher avdo l'chutz la'aretz o
l'chutz la'aretz yatza l'cherut. If you sell him outside of Israel, he
goes free. וצריך שיכשיר מנו רבו שני. ve'tzarich she'yachshir menu rabbo sheni.
The second master is the one that has to free him. So
if the second master has to free him, it means that the
sale took effect, right? If the sale never took effect, you're the
one that has to free him. שמע מינה מדקרי ליה שני רבו,
shema mina mi d'kari lei sheni rabbo, it says the, it calls,
I don't know why he says מדקרי ליה, mi d'kari lei, which
it sounds like it's just a term. I would say since the
second one has the power to free him, but okay. Since it's
calling the second one his master, אלמא לא הדרי זביני, alma lo
hadri zvinei, you see that it did not revert. That sale worked,
and the second master now is the one to free him. וכי
אמר שמואל הכא, ve'chi amar Shmuel hacha, אינו מכור ומעות חוזרים. eino
machur u'ma'ot chozrin.
And when שמואל Shmuel says here it doesn't take effect, means it
doesn't take effect and everybody, and you keep your money. Okay, so
here you try, which makes sense. You try to sell it on
שמיטה, Shmita, the whole point of שמואל Shmuel is that you can't
sell things on שמיטה, Shmita, the sale didn't take effect. There, it
did take effect and then there was a fine. Then we said,
oh, but we don't like this situation, we're going to have to
correct it and therefore the slave has to be freed, but the
sale was effective. Now the גמרא Gemara is about to ask, why
are you going to fine the purchaser rather than the seller? He's
the one that suffers. Okay, but the logic makes sense. Here there's
something intrinsic to sort of, you know, that doesn't allow the sale
to be effective. It's not like we want to correct the situation.
You can't sell it on the יובל Yovel fundamentally. There you sold
it and now we have to try to come and correct it.
Okay, רב ענן, Rav Anan, so why did רב ענן Rav Anan
ask the question if it's explicit in the ברייתא? Braita? ברייתא לא
שמיע ליה, Braita lo shmia lei, he didn't know about the ברייתא.
Braita. It's actually quite interesting, why are they attributing it to שמואל?
Shmuel? It's a ברייתא Braita now that says it. But anyway, okay,
ומשמיה
דשמואל, U'mishmei d'Shmuel, and also of the teaching of שמואל, Shmuel, מאי
דאינה מכורה מעות חוזרים, mai d'eina mechura maot chozrim, it wouldn't be,
it wouldn't have been necessarily obvious that the sale would not be
effective and the money would go back in our case by יובל.
Yovel. דילמא אינה מכורה מעות מתנה. Dilma eina mechura maot matana.
Now, he says, why, what is my other alternative? שמואל Shmuel says
that it's not effective. So of course it's not effective and you
keep the money. What's the alternative? No, there is an alternative. You
could say it's not effective, but maybe when I gave you the
money, we should reinterpret that money as a gift, not I gave
you, I'm the one selling, when here Charlie gives me the money
for my field, okay, so sales of fields can't take place of
שדה אחוזה Sedei Achuza on יובל. Yovel. How do we interpret the
money? Was it a mistake and I give the money back, or
maybe it was a gift? He should be smart enough to know
he can't buy it and obviously this was just a way he
was trying to give me a gift of money. Okay, which is
a little funny, but maybe. So רב ענן Rav Anan understood that
in our case by the field, the sale would never be effective
to begin with. But his question was, how do we interpret the
giving of money? As a mistake and he gets the money back,
or as a gift? Now why would I say such a thing?
Because we've heard in another context שמואל Shmuel actually does say such
a thing. מידי דהוה אהמקדש אחותו, Midi d'hava a'hamikadesh achoto,
like what happened if somebody tried to marry his sister? He gave
his sister some money, a nice gold ring, and he said הרי
את מקודשת לי. Harei at mekudeshet li. דיתמר, D'itmar, המקדש אחותו, hamikadesh
achoto, somebody who tries to marry his sister, רב אמר מעות חוזרים,
Rav amar maot chozrim, give the ring back, okay, the whole thing
was a mistake, give the ring back. ושמואל אמר מעות מתנה. U'Shmuel
amar maot matana. No, it's, yes, it was a mistake, obviously it
didn't take effect, but we interpret the gift as not a mistake,
we interpret it as you should be smart enough to know it's
not effective, and therefore what you're doing is really giving her a
gift. Okay, so there's not a contradiction by the way of the
רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Everybody agrees that מקדש אחותו mekadesh achoto
doesn't take effect. Whereas by יובל Yovel you could say it takes
effect and then יובל Yovel kicks in. Even שמואל Shmuel doesn't contradict
himself, as תוספות Tosafot points out, because you could say that a
person can't marry his sister is patently obvious. So we could, how
do we interpret trying to marry your sister? We could interpret it
as a gift, not as a mistake, it should have been obvious,
whereas by יובל Yovel it's not so obvious. So there we'll understand
that it was a mistake, and since it was a mistake, the
money goes back. Whenever I deal with the kid that מקדש אחותו
mekadesh achoto I'm reminded of this funny story that this רב Rav
comes in at to the ישיבה Yeshiva and he wants to test
the ישיבה Yeshiva guys, he says, so can an אנדרוגינוס Androgynos marry
himself? Right? אנדרוגינוס Androgynos is I guess male and female. So the
ישיבה בחור Yeshiva bachur are thinking, is there an act of נתינה,
netina, you know, they're going back and forth, and he says, of
course not, he's his sister. So anyway,
all right. Okay, מעות מתנה, Maot matana,
it's a very egregious עבירה. aveira. Right, but not עבירה, aveira, not
עבירה aveira to
have sex with your sister.
The act of giving כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin is not an עבירה,
aveira, it's just silly.
So you couldn't give כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin to a married woman?
Yeah, it just doesn't take effect. It doesn't work.
But I mean, you lose the money. Right. What? If she gets
to keep the money, then something happened.
Well, it might be translated, interpreted as a gift, but it's not,
it's certainly a very great breach of propriety, but it's not a
technical עבירה aveira because nothing was binding, there was no act of
sex, right?
But there's more to קידושין kiddushin than just giving, than just giving
something of very small value. There's, isn't there more to?
There's an attempt, there's an attempt to effect a change of status,
but that's not possible in this case because, because the person is
married or your sister or whatever it is. So, so right. Look,
logically you're completely correct. We should say the whole thing was a
mistake and try to just reverse, you know, erase it as much
as possible.
But she shouldn't walk away with.
Right, I understand, I understand. שמואל's Shmuel position is, is strange, but
you know, yeah. He's,
I, yes. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, now
we're going to finish the slave case. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף,
Amar lei Abaye l'Rav Yosef, now we're back to the idea that
the second master is the one that has to free him, so
he's the guy out his money by the slave. מאי חזית דקנסינן
ליה ללוקח, Mai chazit d'kansinan lei l'lokeach, why are you fining the
purchaser and he's the one that's out his money? נקנסיה למוכר, Niknesei
l'mocher, let's fine the one who sells it, which means how would
we fine him? Either by saying the sale isn't binding and now
you have to free, or we can make it a more complicated
case which is you have to buy him back and then free
him. But either way, let's put the burden on the seller, not
on the purchaser. So
אמר ליה, amar lei, לאו עכברא גנב אלא חורא. lav achbara ganav
ela chura. It's not only the weasel that steals, or not the
weasel that steals or the rat, it's the hole that steals, right?
If you don't have a market and you don't have, then the
sellers are not going to be able to ply their trade. Right.
So anyway, so exactly. So this is actually quite fascinating because it
gets to policy questions about the part about people that, you know,
provide a market for people that are engaged in illicit activity. Okay,
so therefore, you know, they have to take the responsibility. Of course,
you might say they have to take part of the responsibility, which
is going to be the response, but not the whole responsibility. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so I'm sorry, the גמרא Gemara says back, one
minute, אי לאו עכברא חורא מנא ליה? Ei lav achbara chura mina
lei? If it weren't for the rat, what good would the hole
would never get the cheese? Meaning yes, the hole is necessary, but
it starts with the rat. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, מי
סברת, Mi savrat, yeah right, but מי סברת היכא דאיתא לדידי קנסינן.
mi savrat heicha de'isa lidi kinsinan. It makes sense that where so
but since each party participates, we're going to fine the person in
where the problem currently resides. So right now the problem is that
the slave is being held by someone who is preventing him from
doing his מצוות, mitzvos, either because he lives in חוץ לארץ Chutz
La'aretz or he's a non-Jew. So therefore, I mean this is assuming
we're in a position to have, you know, that our laws matter
to the non-Jews. But anyway, but the point is yes, but once
we admit that they are both party to this problem, we're going
to address the person who is right now, you know, the focus
of the problem. Yes.
Could this be also an argument against the people who claim who
money who launder money who say I haven't done anything? Right. I
haven't done any illegal activity, I'm just...
Well first of all, it is illegal to launder money. I mean
unless you're talking about like whether הלכתית halachically you are... הלכתית. Halachically.
Oh
yeah, absolutely. This is extremely important. It's all about that idea of
doing the supporting activities that allow that, you know, encourage and enable
other people to do their illicit activities. Absolutely.
So, you know, and it gets also to interesting questions nowadays because
of our sensitivity in terms of, you know, what it means to
be to
you know when we talk about like slave labor in China and
we talk about all these other things to which we provide the
whole market and, you know, the serious financial incentive for all of
these things. So yeah, you can't just you know you can't just
wash your hands from responsibility. Okay, so that was quite fascinating. Now
the גמרא Gemara wraps up the משנה. Mishnah. היתה שנת שידפון, Haysa
shnas shidafon, if it was a year of blight, then it does
not count to the two years. The person can still have use
it for the next year. But if it was his own fault,
like he let it lay fallow or he or he just overturned
the soil but didn't plant it, then that does count towards his
two years. So the גמרא Gemara says, השתא הובירה אמרת ליה, Hashta
hovirah amrat lei, if he just ignored it, like let it lay
waste, it counts towards his two years because it was his own
fault, נירה מיבעיא, neirah mibaya, how much more so if he tried
to start using it like he plowed it, how much more so
does that count towards his two years? So the גמרא Gemara said,
נירה איצטריכא ליה. Neirah itztricha lei. No, there's a חידוש chiddush in
the case of plowing. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka dach amina, I would
have thought to say, and this is important because it goes to
questions everybody was asking yesterday, אמרינן ליה, amrinan lei, הב ליה דמי
פולחנא, hav lei dmei pulchana,
we might say to the owner fine, it's two years, you can
buy it back, but now you're getting a field that's already been
plowed. It's right, you know, it's you now don't have to plow
it, it's just ready for planting. At least pay him for the
plowing that he did. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that we
don't tell you that. He had two years to use it, he
could have used it how he sees fit, now I can buy
it back. Which raises important questions right about this issue about he
made improvements that
how much do I now have to pay when I'm buying it
back for those improvements that he made? Now these are not you
know like structural improvements. These are not like long-standing improvements. It was
just, you know, but it was something that is now benefiting me
and they were saying, oh, you should have used that plowing for
your opportunity, you wasted that opportunity, you know, I don't have to
pay you for that. We will continue to discuss this issue about
what responsibility when I buy it back do I have to factor
into the price improvements that were made to the land. Okay. So
now it wraps up. רבי אליעזר אומר מכר לו. Rabbi Eliezer omer
machar lo. So Rabbi Eliezer says that it's possible to get three
years of grain out of the two years. It goes by two
calendar years, not by the years of grain, depending on when you
sold it. So the גמרא Gemara says, תניא רבי אליעזר אומר מנין
למוכר שדהו לפני ראש השנה מלאה פירות. Tanya Rabbi Eliezer omer minayin
lamocher sadehu lifnei Rosh Hashanah meleiah peiros. How do I know if
he sold it to him before Rosh Hashanah it was filled with
fruit? It's funny it gives the example of fruit and not the
example of like grain, which would have been more before before Pesach.
Anyway, שלא יאמר לו, shelo yomar lo, you don't you can't say
to him, the buyer who's buying it back, הנח לפני כדרך שהנחתי
לפניך. hanach lefanai kederach shehinachti lefanecha. Look, I'm buying it back from
you, I need I'm you have to don't harvest that fruit, I'm
going to buy it back for you at the end of two
years, you have to leave that fruit unharvested so that I get
it back from you the same way I sold it to you.
תלמוד לומר במספר שני תבואות ימכר לך. Talmud lomar bemispar shenei tevuos
yimkor lach. Nope, according to the years of grain, so it goes
by years even if the grain is more than two. פעמים שאדם
אוכל שלש תבואות. Pe'amim she'adam ochel shalosh tevuos. פעמים שאדם אוכל שלש
תבואות בשתי שנים. P'amim she'adam ochel shalosh tevuos b'shtei shanim. Sometimes the
guy can have gotten three harvests out of two years. Now here
it's somewhat the reverse if you think about it on the side
of the opposite of the case we just had before. The before
was the guy who had it for two years contributed and then
I reap the benefit, excuse the metaphor, I gain the benefit, he
plowed it, I get the plow. Here basically, see how do you
do the computation of how much I have to pay him? It's
not based on let's get it reassessed. You take the number, let's
say there were 50 years, you divide the amount paid by 50,
you subtract the two years. So in that case there really is
the seller loses out a bit because Charlie here bought it from
me for two years, he got three harvests out of it, but
he's only going to have to have paid for essentially two out
of 50 years, right? Because of the way we do the math.
Even though he benefited more than an average two years' worth out
of this field because he got three harvests out of those two
years. And nevertheless, if I want it back, I can only deduct
from him two harvests, two years, not more. So that's a little
bit of the reverse of the case of the plowing, that in
this case, there's a fixed way you do the math. He's paid
X amount, X number of years, divide it, pay based on the
remaining years. Even if in one scenario that means that I gain
the plowing he did and he's not getting reimbursed from it, or
even if in the other scenario he gains an extra harvest
and I'm not getting to deduct that from how much I'm paying
him back. Okay, so there's a little obviously can be a little
injustice either way, based on everybody has to know the rules of
the game I guess, but based on the fixed nature of the
system. Okay, let's take a look now at the next משנה. Mishna.
ערכין, Erchin, right?
If you're going to be selling fields during this period, absolutely. I
just think like I said yesterday, it is so much safer if
you're dealing in a time of יובל Yovel to just lease everything.
Why would you want to buy anything? Okay, let's take a look
now at the next משנה. Mishna.
This really gets to cases about difference of values but not because
of capital improvements but because of changing markets and so on. Let's
take a look.
מכרה לראשון במנה ומכרה ראשון לשני במאתים. Machrah l'rishon b'maneh u'machrah rishon
l'sheni b'masayim. So here I take my field, I sell it to
David here for $100. David goes ahead and sells it to Charlie
for 200. Okay, now I want to buy it back off of
Charlie.
How much do I have to pay to buy it back, right?
Do I do it based on the $100 or based on what
I sold it for or based on what Charlie bought it for?
And especially if you imagine that most likely either David is very
shrewd and he knows that he saw that the field was underpriced
or whatever, or the market went up.
But certainly if the market went up, there's a very unfair, Charlie,
because now I'm going to get something worth a lot more money
by just paying back my original amount. So let's take a look.
So what's the הלכה? halacha? So מכרה ראשון לשני במאתים אין מחשב
אלא עם הראשון. Machrah rishon l'sheni b'masayim ein mechashev ela im harishon.
I do the math based on what I paid the first guy.
שנאמר לאיש
אשר מכר לו. Shene'emar l'ish asher machar lo. The person to whom
I sold it to, that serves as the basis. So basically, again,
let's say there were 50 years, I sold it to David for
100, I want to buy it back 25 years in,
half the amount of time, so I only have to pay $50
to get it back. So even though Charlie paid
200 and now the remaining of the time is worth 100, it
doesn't matter. I only have to pay $50. I get it back
from Charlie. Okay, so really it's a big buyer beware system here
when the גאולה... geulah... Okay. אין מחשב אלא... Ein mechashev ela... Now,
מכרה לראשון במאתים ומכרה ראשון
לשני במנה. Machrah l'rishon b'masayim u'machrah rishon l'sheni b'maneh. Let's say it's
the reverse. I sell it to David for 200 and now he
sells it to Charlie for 100. Okay, the market went down, whatever
the case was. Okay, so now I want to buy it back.
It's halfway in, let's say. Do I buy it back at 100
or do I buy it back at 50, right? Do I buy
it back based on what I sold it to you or what
you sold it to him? So אין מחשב אלא עם האחרון. Ein
mechashev ela im ha'acharon. Now I get to use the latter price.
Basically you use whichever system favors the original owner. Okay, which is
שנאמר וחישב את שני ממכרו והשיב את העודף לאיש אשר מכר לו,
Shene'emar v'chishav es shnei mimkaro v'heshiv es ha'odef l'ish asher machar lo,
which we're reading to be לאיש
אשר בתוכו. l'ish asher b'socho. So that since in the end you're
paying, since the פסוקים psukim both refer to the original sale and
to giving it to the person who is now in the land,
it means that either one can serve as the model. Which what
do you pick? You pick the one that
most benefits the seller.
Look, that's one הלכה. halacha. Obviously the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask, given that you could go either way, how do you know
you pick the model that benefits the seller and not the model
that sort of is to the detriment of the seller? Let's just
finish the משנה Mishna and then take your question. A totally different
הלכה. halacha. It says לא ימכור ברחוק ויגאול בקרוב. Lo yimkor b'rachok
v'yigol b'karov.
Let's say I want to get back that field. Now I have
to buy it back. I have to exercise my right to buy
it back, but I don't have any money. What do I do?
Sell a field that I'm less interested in to buy this field
back. Okay, so don't, you're not allowed, don't sell some field you
have that's further away from the city in order to buy this
one. is closer, even though there's a reason you would want to
do that, or ברעה ויגאל ביפה, B'ra'a v'yigoel b'yafa,
don't sell the bad field because you want to buy back a
good field. Okay, the whole point is, you know, you're trying to
hold on, the תורה's Torah invested in you holding on to your
inherited field. Okay, so while in the one, from your financial perspective,
it makes sense for you to sell a less, you know, valuable
field or whatever, a field you're less interested in for this one,
no, you're not supposed to do that. Now, I don't know if
you're not allowed, I mean, it's obviously not that it's not effective,
but that's not the way the תורה Torah sort of is telling
you how you should do the redemption.
ולא ילווה ויגאל, V'lo yilve v'yigoel, don't borrow money in order to
do the redemption. It should only be the cash that you actually
have. Okay, ולא יגאל לחצאין, V'lo yigoel l'chatza'in,
and don't redeem halfway, only you can only redeem the whole thing.
Now that could actually be a restriction, right? Meaning if I show
up to Charlie here, bought from me, and I have the money
and I want to force him to sell it back, is Charlie
entitled to say, oh, I'm sorry, I hear a report that you
borrowed that money, you don't have the, you can't exercise the right?
Probably not. Probably that's just a לכתחילה L'chatchila that I'm not supposed
to have done that. But if I try to buy back half
of it, that presumably is a limit on my right, that Charlie
can say, no, no, no, you either get the whole thing back
or none of it.
Okay, ובהקדש מותר בכולן, U'vehekdesh mutar bekulan, by הקדש Hekdesh you can
do it all. When I sanctify a field, remember, I also have
to try to buy it back, because if I don't buy back
a field I sanctified, it's lost to me completely. But, and there's
a logic here why the גמרא's Gemara going to say this, we
have more latitude by הקדש, Hekdesh, because if you don't buy it
back, it's lost completely. If I don't buy my field back from
Charlie, I'm going to get it back at the יובל Yovel anyway.
So to limit my ability to force Charlie to sell it back
is, makes sense, whereas when I'm getting back from הקדש, Hekdesh, we
want to give me more opportunity or else I'm, it's completely lost.
ובהקדש מותר בכולן, U'vehekdesh mutar bekulan, זה חומר בהדיוט מבהקדש, Ze chomer
b'hedyot m'behekdesh, this way dealing with a layperson is more restrictive than
dealing with הקדש. Hekdesh. By הקדש Hekdesh you can redeem it, you're
allowed to redeem it under a wider range of circumstances. Yes.
So I was going to say, to favor, to automatically favor a
person in a transaction, it looks like the way that הקדש Hekdesh
always moves in transactions, but now in the משנה Mishna we get
an example, the only one I've ever seen where הקדש Hekdesh can
loosen it. Right. Exactly.
Right.
So that's true, although הקדש Hekdesh isn't losing out money in that
scenario. They're not losing money, yeah. They're just making it easier for
you to actually redeem. Okay, what would happen in that case by
הקדש? Hekdesh? Well, there the תורה, Torah, remember, sets a fixed value,
so you don't have these scenarios. Right. Here the value is based
on the original sale, so you can ask about what it's worth.
So let's take a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. מכרה לראשון במנה
ומכרה ראשון לשני במאתים. Machra l'rishon b'maneh u'machra rishon l'sheni b'matayim. מנין
שאין מחשב אלא עם הראשון? Minayin she'ein m'chashev ela im rishon? How
do you know you do it based on the sale to the
first guy, which was the lower amount? תלמוד לומר לאיש אשר מכר
לו. Talmud lomar l'ish asher machar lo. That you pay the money
to the person that you sold it to, that you use that
as the basis for the payment. מכרה לראשון במאתים ומכרה ראשון לשני
במנה. Machra l'rishon b'matayim u'machra rishon l'sheni b'maneh. How about if the
first guy sold, you sold to the first guy for 200, he
sold to the second guy for 100? מנין שאין מחשב אלא עם
השני? Minayin she'ein m'chashev ela im hasheni?
How do you know you do it with the second guy? Meaning
you use the amount set by the second guy, the lesser amount.
תלמוד לומר לאיש, Talmud lomar l'ish, לאיש אשר בתוכו, L'ish asher betocho,
the person who happens to be in it right now. דברי רבי.
Divrei Rebbe. That's what רבי Rebbe said. You take what is to
the benefit of the seller based on the first sale or the
second sale. רבי דוסתאי בן יהודה אומר. Rebbe Dostai ben Yehuda omer.
Now רבי דוסתאי בן יהודה Rebbe Dostai ben Yehuda has a similar
principle that you do the benefit of the seller, but he deals
with a different scenario. Not that there were two sales, there was
one sale but there was a fluctuating market. Okay, so I just
sold it to David here at 100, but then the prices went
up and now it's worth 200, or the reverse. Okay, so you
go by the sale price or the current market price. So let's
take a look. מכר לו במנה. Machar lo b'maneh. I sold it
to somebody for 100. והשביחה, V'hishvicha,
and it improved. Now, and it somehow naturally improved, I don't know,
somehow, you know, there were floods and irrigation or something, or just
the market improved. ועמדה על מאתים, V'amda al matayim, and now it's
worth 200. מנין שאין מחשב אלא במנה? Minayin she'ein m'chashev ela b'maneh?
How do you know you go by not the current market price
but the lower original price? שנאמר והשיב את העודף. Shene'emar v'heshiv et
ha'odef. You pay back the remainder. What does remainder mean? העודף שבידו.
Ha'odef she'beyado.
What remains based on the money that I received. So it focuses
on the money I received and, you know, as if there's a
certain amount per each year and how much money remains based on
the original sale. So remainder means remainder from the original sale. Now,
how about the reverse case? מכר לו במאתים. Machar lo b'matayim. It
was sold for 200. והכסיפה, V'hichsifa, it became worse. Either the market
went down or somehow, you know, again, it got flooded or whatever,
something happened to make it of lesser value. ועמדה במנה, V'amda b'maneh,
it's only worth 100 now. מנין שאין מחשב אלא במנה? Minayin she'ein
m'chashev ela b'maneh? How do you know you go by the current
market price? So again, whether it's the sale price or the current
market price, you do whichever is to the benefit of the seller.
How do you know that? שנאמר והשיב את העודף. Shene'emar v'heshiv et
ha'odef. You return the remainder. העודף שבקרקע. Ha'odef she'bakarka. The remaining value
of the land. Okay, so is it the remaining of the sale
money or the remainder of the value of the land? We interpret
it whichever way is to the benefit of the seller. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask why choose to interpret
it that way, but first we're going to focus on the difference
because they both are talking about a change of value but one
based on a second sale and one based on a change of
the land. So the גמרא Gemara says they don't necessarily agree with
one another. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו, Mai beinaihu, what's
the difference between them? דיקר וזל ודיקר. Deyakar u'zal u'deyakar.
It went- it was high, low, and high. Meaning what happened? It
means let's say
I sold this to David for 200. He sold it to Charlie
for 100. But now the market value is 200. Okay, so it
went up again. Okay, dot dot dot. So now, according to the
one that says you focus on the original sale price- original sale
price and the current market value, well the original sale price was
200, the current market value is 200, I would have to use
the 200 model. But according to רבי Rebbi that goes by the
sale prices, if there's more than one sale price, so I can
still now buy it back from David for 100- from Charlie for
100 because that was the second sale price. So it has nothing
to do with the current market price, it all has to do
with the various sale prices. Okay, is that clear or not? One
of them says everybody agrees you do if there's two options, you
do what's to the benefit of the seller. But what- but they
don't agree that you look at all the factors. One says you
look at the factors of multiple purchase prices. If there are multiple
purchase prices to look at, you do the one that's the lowest.
That's רבי, Rebbi, that's our משנה. Mishna. The other one says no,
you look at the sort of original purchase price and current market
value. Okay, so those are different ways of figuring it out to
the benefit of the seller, but they don't necessarily coincide. Right, purchase
prices and market prices are not always the same thing. Okay. Okay,
so let's- or a simpler example תוספות Tosafot says is that there
was no second sale. I sold this to David for 200, it's
now worth 100. According to רבי Rebbi it still goes on 200,
it all goes by purchase prices. Whereas according to- according to the
second opinion, it goes by also looking at current market prices. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask why we interpret
this whichever we do it, whichever points we look at, why do
we do it to the benefit of the seller? וממאי דלקולא דילמא
לחומרא? Umimai d'lekula dilma l'chumra?
Since you read the פסוקים Psukim to point to the fact that
it could be either the original or the later point, why do
you choose to read it that way that you do it to
the benefit of the seller? Why not do it to the- to
the detriment of the seller? דילמא לחומרא? Dilma l'chumra? So the גמרא
Gemara says לא סלקא דעתך, Lo salka datach, that doesn't make sense.
דגמר גאולה גאולה מעבד עברי, Degamar geula geula me'eved ivri,
that we learn a גזירה שוה Gzeira shava here it says redeeming
and by עבד עברי Eved ivri if somebody sells himself as a
slave it says that his relatives should redeem him. And the same
way there we have a similar principle and there it's lenient for
the benefit of the עבד Eved of the slave, here it will
be the same. So now we have to demonstrate that we have
the same principle by a slave and that there we know that
it's to the benefit of the seller. So let's take a look.
והתם מנלן, Ve'hatam minalan, where do we know that by the slave
there's the same principle and that it's to his benefit? דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא. Braita. נמכר במנה והשביח ועמד על מאתיים.
Nimkar be'maneh ve'hishbiach ve'amad al matayim. Now by the slave the same
principle by the way is true. Somebody sells himself as a slave,
a Jew sells himself as an עבד עברי, Eved ivri, he is
entitled to force the master to free him if he can get
the money and buy back his own freedom. Okay, that's the same
idea of גאולה. Geula. I mean again, that's the emphasis of the
תורה Torah in בהר, Behar, which is that you're fundamentally entitled to
your freedom, you're fundamentally entitled to your ancestral lands, so even if
you sell them away you always have the right to sort of,
you know, to- to gain them back, to pay the money and
to gain them back. That's the גאולה, Geula, redemption. It's not just
an idea of purchase, right, it's redeeming, it's restoring things to their
natural state. So how do we know now the question is again,
what if there are different prices? So נמכר במנה והשביח ועמד על
מאתיים, Nimkar be'maneh ve'hishbiach ve'amad al matayim, he sold himself for 100
and now he's worth 200. Again, he got healthier, he got- he
exercised or just the market went up, whatever it is. מניין שאין
מחשבין אלא במנה? Minal she'ein mechasvin ela be'maneh? How do you know
that he can buy himself back based on the original price, 100?
שנאמר מכסף מקנתו, Shene'emar mikesef miknato,
that he redeems himself from the money of the sale. So you
look at the original money of the sale. Again, and you do
it proportional to the years that remain, right, not the full amount
but proportional to the years that remain. Now how about the reverse?
נמכר במאתיים והכסיף ועמד על מנה, Nimkar be'matayim ve'hichsif ve'amad al maneh,
he was sold for 200 and he got sick or injured or
whatever or the market went down and he's only worth 100. מניין
שאין מחשבין אלא ממנה? Minal she'ein mechasvin ela mimaneh? How do you
know he can buy himself back based on the rate of 100,
not the rate of 200? שנאמר כפי שניו, Shene'emar kefi shaniv,
according to the remaining years, so you look at the value that
he represents for the remaining years, you don't look at the original
market price. Right. ואין לי עבד עברי הנמכר לעובד כוכבים שנגאל וידו
על העליונה. Ve'ein li eved ivri hanimkar l'oved kochavim shenigal ve'yado al
ha'elyona. How do I know if it's an- if it's a Jewish
slave sold to a non-Jew, right, which is what the תורה Torah
describes in one scenario in בהר, Behar, that is redeemed, וידו על
העליונה, Ve'yado al ha'elyona, and you want to sort of, you know,
assuming again that the Jews have control over those situations and you
want to really, you know, get him out of the- being owned
by the non-Jew. נמכר לישראל מניין, Nimkar l'yisrael minal, how do you
know even if he's sold to a Jew the same thing is
true that it's to his- you always read it to his benefit?
תלמוד לומר שכיר שכיר לגזירה שוה. Talmud lomar sachir sachir l'gzeira shava.
So we make a גזירה שוה Gzeira shava here it says שכיר
Sachir when it's talking about being sold to a
non-Jew and it
says... Now, so we see the same principle, but we really have
the same question there too. The פסוקים pesukim can be interpreted to
go by the original price, to go by the remaining price. Who
says you interpret it to the benefit of the slave and not
to the benefit of the master? So saying the גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah doesn't still answer the question, how do you know which way
to interpret it? So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, and now we're going
to get to that. So אביי Abaye said, this is a famous
phrase that אביי Abaye said sometimes, הריני כבן עזאי בשוקי טבריה. hareini
k'Ben Azzai b'shukei Tverya. He's like feeling so good, he says, I'm
like בן עזאי Ben Azzai in the marketplaces of טבריה. Tverya. What
does that mean? So apparently, if you remember actually, בן עזאי Ben
Azzai sometimes, this was at the end of בכורות, Bechorot, you know,
sort of would sometimes be feeling so good about himself and say
like,
none of the sages are worth anything compared to me. So apparently,
and he lived in טבריה, Tverya, so he would go around saying
that in טבריה. Tverya. So אביי Abaye was feeling very good about
himself one day, and he basically said, I'll take on all challengers.
Okay, so that people are going to sort of see, this is
usually like a lead-up for a little bit of a deflation. Okay,
so אמר ליה ההוא מרבנן לאביי. amar lei hahu me-rabbanan l'Abaye. So
one of the rabbis said to אביי, Abaye, oh, I have a
question, let's see if you can answer this. איכא דדרשינהו לקולא ואיכא
דדרשינהו לחומרא. ika d'darshinhu l'kula v'ika d'darshinhu l'chumra. With these פסוקים, pesukim,
you could, okay, you could say that there are two points you
could look at, but you could make it to lenient, meaning to
the benefit of the seller or the slave, or you could make
it strict, to their detriment. ממאי דלקולא אימא לחומרא? mimai d'l'kula eima
l'chumra? How do you know that you make it to their benefit?
Maybe you make it to their detriment? לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka
datach.
That doesn't make sense. Because, and now here's we see why it's
better that we've introduced the idea of slave, because we're going to
use the slave model as a sort of to, you know, as
an intuitive argument about why we want to be lenient. Right? I
mean, I think it's more obvious, right? There's a clear sense that
we're going to try to make it easier for the slave to
get free. And once we prove it by the slave, we can
prove it also by the, we can link it to the field.
Okay, מדאחיל רחמנא גביה. mid'achil Rachmana gabei. Since the תורה Torah is
lenient, you know, or cares about the interests of the slave. דתניא,
detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, כי טוב לו עמך, ki
tov lo imach, it is good for him with you. רש"י, Rashi,
תוספות Tosafot says that that's really just a descriptive verse. He prefers
the פסוק pasuk of כי שכיר יהיה עמך, ki sachir yihyeh imach,
which is a מצוה. mitzvah. He shall be like a שכיר sachir
with you. But the emphasis is the word with you. עמך במאכל
עמך במשתה. imach b'ma'achal imach b'mishteh.
You should treat him as an equal when it comes to food,
when it comes to drink. שלא תהא אתה אוכל פת נקייה והוא
אוכל פת קיבר. shelo tehei atah ochel pat nekiyah v'hu ochel pat
kivar. You shouldn't eat the white bread and he eats the bran
bread. This was before people chose to eat bran bread willingly. אתה
שותה יין ישן והוא שותה יין חדש. atah shoteh yayin yashan v'hu
shoteh yayin chadash. You drink the nice old wine
and he drinks the young wine. אתה ישן על גבי מוכין והוא
ישן על גבי קרקע. atah yashen al gabei mochin v'hu yashen al
gabei karka. You sleep on nice cushions or, you know, whatever pillows,
and
he sleeps on the ground. You have to treat your slave as
your equal. מכאן אמרו, mikan amru, from here they said, הקונה עבד
עברי כקונה אדון לעצמו. hakoneh eved ivri k'koneh adon l'atzmo. Right? Which
is a real reverse, but obviously it's, you know, an embodiment of
the תורה's Torah concern of לבני ישראל עבדים. li-vnei Yisrael avadim. I
mean, we're about to read משפטים, Mishpatim, you know, the whole, one
of the very first מצוות mitzvot is about, about sort of undermining
the institution of slavery. So, you know, חז"ל Chazal do that by
really, you know, continuing that approach by reading the פסוק pasuk to
say that you have to treat him almost as an equal. So
you really are, you know, you don't get to act as a
master over him. So therefore, if that's true, then clearly the תורה
Torah is concerned with him not being a slave, and therefore clearly
it'll make it easier for him to redeem himself.
Yes, but that still doesn't, so this, why not?
No, once we've linked, because we had a פסוק pasuk that linked
the slave, remember גאולה גאולה geulah geulah linked the slave to the
field.
Right, and so we've shown, proved that it's, that the slave is
going to be treated in a lenient way for this particular,
oh, so let's see, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to
say. Okay, yes.
Does the sold daughter gets treated, does she get treated as a
slave? She's just a wife.
If she, if the money used for the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin
for the, for the purchase money to buy the underage daughter is
turned into כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, then she's a wife.
Then she's treated like any wife.
But if she, but if not, then she's treated like any slave
to the same הלכות. halachot. Yes, this is not just limited to
a male slave. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
אדרבה. aderaba. So now the, it's going to be, okay, good, there's
some areas where we're very nice, but it doesn't prove we're nice
in all cases. נחמיר עליהם. nachmir aleihem. Maybe we should be strict
on this guy. Why? And make it harder to redeem him. Why?
מדיהושע בן חנינא? mi-d'Yehoshua ben Chanina? No, it's רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא.
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina. Based on the teaching of רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina. דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, d'amar Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Chanina, בוא וראה כמה קשה אבקה של שביעית. bo u're'eh
kamah kashah avkah shel shevi'it. Come and see how, you know, difficult,
meaning how consequential the, the consequences are of even the dust of
שמיטה, shmita, of not being sensitive, of not being careful about even
the lighter laws relating to שמיטה. shmita. Why? And what he's going
to do is he's going to basically interpret the flow of the
פסוקים pesukim in בהר. Behar. Because בהר Behar opens with, and I'll
just read you the beginning of the פסוקים, pesukim, it opens with
obviously the laws of שמיטה shmita about not working the land. And
then it goes on the following way, it says, where does it
start? Okay, and then it says, so he counts the years. Then
it says after
that וכי ימוך אחיך ומכר מאחוזתו ve-khi yamukh achikha u-makhar me-achuzato again
selling your
inherited plot. ואיש כי
ימכור בית מושב עיר חומה ve-ish ki yimkor beit moshav ir chomah
what if you sell a house in a walled city? וכי ימוך
אחיך ומטה ידו עמך ve-khi yamukh achikha u-matah yado imakh and what
if you wind up having to sell yourself? And then redeeming slaves
and it goes on. So he's going to understand that this is
one thing leads to another. That somebody sinned with שמיטה Shmita led
to them having to sell their fields, led to them having to
sell their house, to sell themselves as slaves. All of this is
because of the consequences. You're trying to make a profit by violating
הלכה, halakha, you will suffer the
consequence. So let's take a look. אדם נושא ונותן בפירות שביעית, adam
nosei ve-noten be-peirot shevi'it,
a person deals with selling שמיטה Shmita produce, which is just the
dust of שמיטה Shmita because the most weighty prohibitions of שמיטה Shmita
are working the land. You didn't work the land. You just went
and wanted to make a profit, you went into the you know
you sold and bought שמיטה Shmita produce. What happens? לסוף מוכר את
מטלטליו, le-sof mokher et metaltelev, you wind up first of all selling
your chattel, שנאמר she-ne'emar בשנת היובל הזאת תשובו איש אל אחוזתו. bi-shnat
ha-yovel ha-zot tashuvu ish el achuzato.
So first it speaks about the יובל yovel and going back. וכתיב
ve-khitiv וכי תמכרו ממכר לעמיתך או קנה מיד עמיתך. ve-khi timkeru mimkar
l'amitekha o kano mi-yad amitekha. If you sell something or buy something.
Now again the context there means you're selling your field, but חז"ל
Chazal understand it דבר הנקנה מיד ליד davar ha-nikneh mi-yad le-yad chattel,
because they learned it that's the prohibition of overcharging, which is particularly
in the case of selling מטלטלין metaltelin and chattel. So first you
tried to make a profit. First thing that starts to happen is
you start becoming poor and you have to start
selling all of your chattel. לא הרגיש, lo hirgish, you were not
sensitive to the fact that there was a reason this was happening
to you and therefore you did not do תשובה. teshuvah. You should
have woken up but you didn't and you didn't do תשובה. teshuvah.
לסוף מוכר שדותיו, le-sof mokher sadotav, then you wind up selling your
fields, שנאמר she-ne'emar וכי ימוך אחיך
ומכר מאחוזתו. ve-khi yamukh achikha u-makhar me-achuzato. Then the next פסוק pasuk
talks about selling your actual inheritance.
לא באו לידו lo ba'u le-yado and if you still were not
aware of the problem of why this was happening to you and
you didn't do תשובה, teshuvah, לסוף מוכר ביתו, le-sof mokher beito, then
you'll wind up selling your house, שנאמר she-ne'emar the next פרשה parshah
says, the next paragraph,
ואיש כי ימכור בית מושב עיר חומה. ve-ish ki yimkor beit moshav
ir chomah. It should be ביתו. beito. What is it? ואיש כי
ימכור בית
מושב עיר חומה. ve-ish ki yimkor beit moshav ir chomah. Anyway and
it's going to go on. But the גמרא Gemara interjects. It doesn't
let it continue the narrative because it picks up on a different
use of terminology. So here's an interjection of the גמרא. Gemara. One
minute. מאי שנא התם דקאמר לא הרגיש mai shena hatam de-ka'amar lo
hirgish when it first said that you did something wrong, it says
if you weren't sensitive to it you'll wind up selling your land.
ומאי שנא
הכא דקאמר לא באו לידו u-mai shena hacha de-ka'amar lo ba'u le-yado
and then it says and if you were oblivious to it, which
is like לא באו לידו, lo ba'u le-yado, then you'll wind up
selling your house and you don't do תשובה. teshuvah. So why does
it use a different phrase to say you didn't wake up to
the fact that it was happening for a reason? כדי רב הונא.
kidei Rav Huna. This is to implicitly teach you a teaching of
רב הונא. Rav Huna. דאמר רב הונא, de-amar Rav Huna, רב הונא
Rav Huna says, כיון שעבר אדם עבירה ושנה בה, keivan she-avar adam
aveirah ve-shanah bah, once a person has done a sin and repeated
it, הותרה לו, hutrah lo, it becomes permissible to him. So the
גמרא Gemara says הותרה לו סלקא דעתך, hutrah lo salka da'atakh, you
mean that objectively that once you do an עבירה aveirah twice it's
permissible? No. אלא אימא נעשית לו כהיתר. ela eima na'asit lo ke-heter.
It's as if permissible. Once you've done it twice, you're no longer
aware that you're doing something wrong. You do it once, you know
you're doing something wrong but you rationalize it but you're a little
sensitive. So the first time it says לא הרגיש. lo hirgish. לא
הרגיש lo hirgish means you're aware but you're not responding as you
should respond. You have a sense that something is wrong but you
didn't respond to it. The second time לא באו לידו, lo ba'u
le-yado, you were completely oblivious because you had already now continued doing
the sin and you're not doing תשובה teshuvah and you're getting more
and more entrenched so you remain even that much more oblivious. So
in a way maybe God is sending you more of a wake-up
call by making your situation worse and worse, at the same time
you are perpetuating the sin and becoming more and more oblivious. רבי
ישראל סלנטר Rabbi Yisrael Salanter had a great line. He says the
גמרא Gemara says if you did it once, once you've done a
sin, you do a sin once it's a sin, you do it
twice it's like a היתר, heter, he says you do it three
times it's like a מצוה. mitzvah.
Right? So what do you think Seth? Can you identify with that
in your profession there? Our ability to certainly rationalize our behavior.
Turn it to good.
Exactly, exactly. You take all the bad stuff and we explain to
ourselves why what we're doing really is a good thing. Anyway, focus.
So the גמרא Gemara says anyway, so you're getting more and more
perpetuating your sinning and selling פירות שביעית peirot shevi'it and you're not
waking up to all these things. We'll skip the parenthesis. לא באו
לידו, lo ba'u le-yado, now you didn't wake up even after you
had to sell your house, after you sold your field, what did
you do? Yeah, you sold your house. לא באו לידו עד שמוכר
את בתו. lo ba'u le-yado ad she-mokher et bito. So now after
you sold your house, now you wind up selling your daughter. daughter.
שנאמר She'ne'emar but of course this is not part of the narrative
in בהר. Behar. בהר Behar doesn't mention selling your daughter. It mentions
selling yourself next. The next paragraph is selling yourself. שנאמר She'ne'emar וכי
ימכור איש את בתו לאמה, Ve'chi yimkor ish et bito le'amah, if
a man sells his daughter for a slave. This is coming week's
פרשה. parsha. ואף על גב Ve'af al gav says the גמרא Gemara
דבתו בהאי עניינא ליתא, de'bito be'hai inyana leita,
although the selling one's daughter is not mentioned in בהר, Behar, we
would assume that before you wound up selling yourself, you're going to
sell your daughter. Okay, so because the next part is selling yourself.
ניחא ליה לאיניש דליזבן ברתיה, Nichla le'inish de'lizban barteh, I'm sorry, and
actually the next פרשה parsha is also borrowing ולא ליזף בריביתא. ve'lo
lizaf be'ribita.
I'm sorry, the next פרשה parsha before selling yourself is borrowing with
ריבית. ribis. One let's take a look. וכי ימוך אחיך, Ve'chi yamuch
achicha, oh yeah, אל תקח מאתו נשך ותרבית. al tikach me'ito neshech
ve'tarbit. Okay, so after it speaks about selling your house and before
it gets to selling yourself, it talks about borrowing with interest. So
the גמרא Gemara inserts that there's something else you could do after
you sold your house before you had to either sell yourself or
borrow interest, and that's sell your daughter. And we assume people would
do that. Why would they? דאילו התם מיגרע, De'ilu hatam migra, because
by the daughter, right, it'll be the buyback price gets lower as
time proceeds. So you sold her, you got a hundred dollars for
her, and now you can always buy her back even at a
lesser amount because it's getting close, you know, it's only for a
limited, you know, you do it proportional. דאילו הכא, De'ilu hacha, and
if you borrow money with interest,
קמוסיף ואזיל, kamosif ve'azil, your debt increases. So in one place your
debt decreases and the other increases. So if we're trying to imagine
a person sort of sinking lower and lower, so presumably he would
at this stage sell his daughter. And then pay interest?
No, no, no,
meaning the תורה Torah says, the תורה Torah says after the selling
of the house it talks about a scenario of borrowing with interest.
So the גמרא Gemara says presumably before a person is going to
borrow with interest in a way that his debt will constantly be
increasing, he'll choose to sell his daughter first rather than to put
himself in a situation where he's constantly...
Not because he's concerned about the prohibition of interest, but because it's
going to cost him more money.
Right. Well, we're imagining exactly that. A person that's unconcerned, who's not
waking up, is just, you know, and is only concerned about money
and is suffering all these things and not waking up to his
responsibilities.
So then it says, okay, לא בא לידו, lo vas le'yado, he
still remains oblivious. לסוף שמוכר את עצמו. Le'sof she'mocher et atzmo. I
mean, obviously the interest should be stuck in here and that was
a line sort of earlier. So anyway, presumably then he does the
interest. If he still doesn't wake up, then he winds up selling
himself. שנאמר She'ne'emar כי ימוך אחיך עמך ונמכר לך. ki yamuch achicha
imach ve'nimkar lach. So and he gets sold to you. So that's
sold to a Jew. לא לך, Lo lecha, not only will he
sell himself to a Jew, אלא לגר, ela le'ger, he'll even sell
himself to a, either convert or to a, to a גר תושב,
ger toshav, a resident alien, שנאמר לגר. she'ne'emar le'ger. ולא לגר צדק,
Ve'lo le'ger tzedek, not a convert, אלא לגר תושב, ela le'ger toshav,
a resident alien, not even to a Jew, שנאמר לגר תושב. she'ne'emar
le'ger toshav. And then it says משפחת גר, mishpachat ger, when it
says a family of the sojourner, זה עובד כוכבים. zeh oved kochavim.
That's even somebody that is completely, you know, not even a resident
alien, a complete non-Jew, complete foreigner. שהוא אומר או לעקר משפחת גר,
She'hu omer o le'eker mishpachat ger, what does that word mean עקר,
eker, the root of the family, whatever, זה הנמכר ונעשה משרת לעובד
כוכבים עצמו. zeh hanimkar ve'na'aseh mesharet le'oved kochavim atzmo. Somebody will even
wind up selling himself to serve in a
non-in a, you know, in a pagan temple. This is how far
you will fall. Okay. Well, yes, exactly, exactly. That's a good point.
Right, and that's a good actually I didn't think about that, but
you know that's actually you're right, the way the תוכחה tochacha is
phrased, which is,
which is right before this, right, is about that, is about like,
you know, ואם בזאת לא תשמעו לי, ve'im be'zot lo tishme'u li,
it's exactly that, that you're suffering and you're not waking up. That's
an excellent point. I mean, not actually, it's actually immediately follows it.
Right. That's a very, that's a very good point. So you're right.
So they're almost taking this story about, you know, about things getting
worse and worse and they're framing it as you didn't wake up,
which exactly parallels the תוכחה tochacha which follows. It's an excellent point.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says fine. Anyway,
okay. So now what do we see? We see that if you
sell yourself, presumably it's because you did all this bad stuff. So
therefore, why should we be so sensitive to try to make it
easier for you to redeem yourself? Maybe this is justified punishment. I
should say that that's like a dangerous theology because, you know, in
the certainly in the non-Jewish and in pagan beliefs, there was this
theology of, I forget there was a name for it, but it
basically was that if you're successful it means that you're loved by
the gods and if you're not successful it means that you're
not, which basically means that you don't have a responsibility for people
that are suffering because obviously they're what they get they you know
what they deserve. Exactly. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara is saying,
oh, so if we have this whole explanation here, maybe we shouldn't
care that the guy is a slave and we shouldn't try to
make it easier.
But this is a very strange...
Yes, someone violating שביעית Shevi'it and ruining your life, ruining your daughter,
losing everything.
So that's an interesting question.
Well, that's an interesting question too. Does the גמרא Gemara mean it
in a... sense of like theological, you know, of like divinely ordained
punishment? Right. Well, right.
It's so weighty.
Yes. So okay. So that I don't know. I mean I'm not
sure if שביעית Shevi'is more than anything or it's just used I
mean you're right it starts with come and see how weighty שביעית
Shevi'is is, but it might also just be used as a message
for right it just might be used for more of a general
message of sin and violation
that maybe you don't think is all that important.
Right. Well, yeah, I understand. Oh, you mean a general light treating
of a commandment. Right. It also could be, you know, a moral
message that somebody that is so focused on financial gain to the
fact that it doesn't matter how they gain the money, you know,
can then, you know, can wind up their pursuit of money can
wind like a lot of these things are things that you're doing
because you don't care how they hurt people. All you care about
is money. So I think that that's maybe you can read this
sort of like as a moral message, not just as a divine
punishment.
Well, that also that's the problem.
I know, but I'm saying I'm saying you don't but you can
read it. I feel guilty. I understand, but that happens all the
time that there are people that are so interested in their own
interest that they don't care who they hurt. So I'm saying you
could read this as a moral message about the way this person
is acting, not about a divinely ordained punishment. Okay. And I think
that that's somewhat implicit. He then he does this and then he
does this. It's sort of this is the type of choices such
a person winds up making. All right, so let's see how the
גמרא Gemara concludes this. It says אמר ליה אסתייעא דקרא, Amar lei
astaye'a de-kra,
one minute he says, the
פסוק's pasuk very nice I agree with you that he maybe brought
it upon himself, but the פסוק pasuk still tells us that we
still have to care about him. So even if he brought it
upon himself, it's still our obligation to care about him. ותנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל, Ve-tana devei Rabbi Yishmael, הואיל והלך ומכר עצמו לעבודת כוכבים,
ho'il ve-halach u-machar atzmo la-avodas kochavim,
maybe I should say since this guy sold himself to a non-Jew
or even like to a pagan temple, ידחי אבן אחר הנופל, idchi
even achar ha-nofel, that's a great little phrase in the גמרא. Gemara.
Maybe I should throw a rock on top of the person who
fell down. Okay, which means like, you know, do I think I'm
entitled? Look, he did it to himself, let's just finish it off,
let's just not care about him completely, throw a rock on top
of him. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so the פסוק pasuk is, and
he again quotes the פסוק, pasuk, גאולה תהיה לו אחד מאחיו יגאלנו.
Ge'ulah tihyeh lo echad me-echav yigalenu. No,
even if he went ahead and sold himself to a pagan temple,
we have a responsibility to redeem him. Okay. אימא גאולה תהיה לו.
Eima ge'ulah tihyeh lo. So the גמרא Gemara says fine, I accept
we have a responsibility to redeem him, but I'm still not willing
to concede the point. אימא גאולה תהיה לו, Eima ge'ulah tihyeh lo,
שלא יטמע בעבודת כוכבים. she-lo yitamei be-avodas kochavim. Fine,
we have to redeem him, we can't let him become totally sort
of, you know, immersed among in the pagan amongst the pagans. ולעולם
לעניין פדיונו נחמיר בו. U-le-olam le-inyan pidyono nachmir bo. But when we
figure out the amount of money, then maybe and if there are
two points to look at, maybe we have to do the stricter
point. Meaning, I accept there are all these things that we care
about him. You have to treat him equally, we have responsibility to
redeem him, but it still doesn't prove that we know that when
you have to choose whether it's the original purchase point or the
current amount that we do the lower amount. So let's just finish
this up. אלא אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Ela amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, although now it's getting to be more and more convincing
if you're doing all those things why not do that? But again,
the point is I would say let's not also forget the interests
of the one who bought him. He paid good money, why should
he be hurt, you know, you know, just because we want to
redeem this slave? So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, כתיב, Kesiv, the verse says, אם עוד רבות בשנים. Im
od rabos ba-shanim. If there's a lot of years left or there's
multiplicity of the years. וכתיב ואם מעט נשאר בשנים, Ve-chesiv ve-im me'at
nish'ar ba-shanim, if there's a little left in the years. So he
says, it doesn't say if there's a lot of years, there's a
few years. He says if there's, you know, if there's many of
the years or whatever, the phrase is a funny phrase. So he
says, וכי יש שנים מרובות ויש שנים מועטות? Ve-chi yesh shanim merubos
ve-yesh shanim mu'atos? It sounds like the years themselves, not that there's
many units of years, but the years themselves are bigger or the
years themselves are smaller. That doesn't make sense. אלא, Ela, here's what
it means. נתרבה כספו, Nitraba kaspo, אם עוד רבות בשנים, im od
rabos ba-shanim,
meaning if the value is now greater than מכסף מקנתו, mi-kesef miknaso,
because the verse actually says אם עוד רבות בשנים כפי הן ישיב
גאולתו מכסף מקנתו. im od rabos ba-shanim kefi hen yashiv ge'ulaso mi-kesef
miknaso.
So when it says many, it ends with מכסף מקנתו, mi-kesef miknaso,
the purchase price. So meaning if now the value is greater, you
go back מכסף מקנתו mi-kesef miknaso to the original purchase price. נתמעט
כספו, Nitma'at kaspo, then it says ואם מעט נשאר בשנים, ve-im me'at
nish'ar ba-shanim, כפי שניו. kefi shaniv.
You redeem him according to the years. So meaning if the value
is less, then you look at the years that remain. Okay. So
meaning it's a very brilliant read of the פסוק. pasuk. He says
the word that refers to going back to the original purchase price,
מכסף מקנתו, mi-kesef miknaso, is linked to the phrase many, which I'm
going to read as the value increased. If the value increased, you
go back to the original purchase price. Then the word that says
כפי שניו, kefi shaniv, the remaining years, which means you look at
the current value, that's linked to the word מעט, me'at, which means
if the value has gone down, then you look at the remaining
value. So we're actually going to get it from a close read
of the פסוק pasuk itself. So then the גמרא Gemara has one
last attempt to defend it. ואימא היכא דעבד תרתי ופייש ארבע, Ve-eima
heicha de-avad tarti u-fayesh arba, ליסב ליה ארבע מכסף מקנתו, leisiv lei
arba mi-kesef miknaso, והיכא דעבד ארבע ופייש תרתי, ve-heicha de-avad arba u-fayesh
tarti, ליסב ליה תרתי כפי שניו. leisiv lei tarti kefi shaniv.
Maybe it should not be whether the value goes up and down,
but whether there's more years left, more years that he's served or
more years that he's... If he's served two years and there's four
years left, then you go by the original price. If he's served
four and there's two years left, then you go by the current
price or maybe a lot and a little does not mean the
prices fluctuated, but whether there's more or less years behind him or
in front of him. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אם כן
נכתוב אם עוד רבות שנים, im ken nichtov im od rabot shanim,
if there's many years. מה בשנים? mah bashanim?
The multiplicity is in the year itself, which means that the value
of each year is higher or the value of each year is
lower. נתרבה כספו בשנים מכסף מקנתו, nisrabeh kaspo bashanim mikesef miknato,
if now the value of the years has gone up, the value,
then you go to the original lower original purchase price. נתפשטו כספו
בשנים, nispashtu kaspo bashanim, if the value of each year is worth
less, the value has gone down, כפי שניו kefi shaniv you look
at the current value. Okay, so that was רב נחמן בר יצחק's
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak's answer, a brilliant close read of the פסוק,
pasuk, so rather than just this larger, if you would like, moral
message, which is also pretty persuasive, and the גמרא Gemara ends with
the following statement: אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, פשינו רב נחמן להני קראי כסיני. pashinu Rav Nachman l'hanei
kra'i k'Sinai. רב נחמן Rav Nachman interpreted those פסוקים pesukim like they
came from הר סיני. Har Sinai. And I want to say one
last thing which occurs to me about רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. There's
a famous debate at the end of קידושין Kiddushin between רבה Rabbah
and רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, which is better: סיני Sinai or עוקר
הרים? oker harim? Meaning, somebody who has
knowledge, erudition, like you got it from הר סיני, Har Sinai, or
somebody that has strong ability of analysis, עוקר הרים, oker harim, like
you can grind things together. And רב יוסף Rav Yosef says סיני
עדיף, Sinai adif, that it's better to have it by tradition. But
here what we have is somebody figures this out based on רב
נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak based on his sharp analysis.
So
I think רב יוסף Rav Yosef is saying, ah, here for once
your analysis was so good, it's as if you got it from
סיני. Sinai. I still think it's better to have it all from
מסורה masorah and tradition, but here actually it's good enough, it's as
good as if you actually had it from the tradition, from סיני.
Sinai. Okay.